Theodore Bowie papers>, 1914-2008 C697
Indiana University Archives
Theodore Bowie papers
1914-2008
1930-1995
Indiana University Archives
Bowie, Theodore Robert
C697
5.8 cubic feet 7 boxes
Theodore Bowie was a prominent faculty member at Indiana University, whose contributions to the field of the history of Asian Art made him a pivotal figure in the development of both the University's Art History Program and the University's Art Museum. This collection contains materials from both Bowie's professional and personal career. Professional documents from his time spent as professor and curator include lecture notes, travel itineraries, copies of scholarly publications, departmental memos and correspondence, loan agreements for exhibitions, and exhibition catalogues. A large number of exhibition materials pertain to "The Arts of Thailand", a traveling exhibition organized by Bowie that showcased previously unrecognized Thai art in the West. Accompanying these professional documents are Bowie's personal correspondence, drafts of his memoir, and a large number of photos and exhibition scrapbooks.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Biographical Note
Theodore R. "Ted" Bowie was a prominent faculty member at Indiana University, whose contributions to the field of the history of Asian Art made him a pivotal figure in the development of the University's Art History Program. Bowie's research and travel in Asia would contribute to a number of acquisitions for exhibitions which he organized, and inform his work in the development of the University Art Museum. His exhibition "The Arts of Thailand", opening at the Museum in 1960, would become one of the first of its kind to display Thai art in the West, going on to travel throughout the United States, Europe, and Asia.
Bowie was born in Nagasaki, Japan, in 1905 to a Russian mother and American father and grew up in both Nice, France, and San Francisco. Bowie received his bachelor's degree from the University of California at Berkeley in 1927 and stayed on to earn his master's degree in political science in 1929, and his doctorate in French literature in 1935. Turning from his early career in French literature, Bowie would go on to fulfill a number of roles relating to the study of art and art history at Indiana University.
Beginning his career at Indiana University in 1950, Bowie would serve as Associate Professor in the Department of Fine Arts from 1950 to 1960. He then served as Associate Professor in the Graduate School from 1952 to 1960, and Professor from 1960 to 1975. While at IU, Bowie would also serve as Fine Arts Librarian from 1951 to 1960, as an unofficial Curator of Oriental Collections at the University Art Museum from 1962 to 1976, as Acting Chair of the Department of Fine Arts from 1970 to 1973, and as Chairman of the Arts Administration Program from 1969 to 1972. He received the title of Professor Emeritus upon his retirement in 1975.
Theodore Bowie died of heart failure on March 5, 1995 in his home in Bloomington, Indiana in the company of his wife Marilyn (Miller) Bowie.
Arrangement
The collection organized into four series: Biographical, Correspondence, Professional-subdivided into research, publications and collected materials, and Photograph Albums. Folders within each series are organized alphabetically.
Scope and Content Note
The collection spans the years 1914 to 2008, with the bulk of the materials from 1930 to 1995. The collection includes items pertaining to both Bowie's work and personal life. A large number of the items included were generated by exhibitions organized by Bowie, many for the IU Art Museum, and from his time spent as a prominent faculty member at Indiana University in the Department of Fine Art. Many of the exhibition documents, including gallery guides, catalogues, and installation photos, pertain to "The Arts of Thailand" exhibition in 1960, one of the first of its kind in the West.
The documents relating to Bowie's professional life include lecture notes, travel itineraries, copies of scholarly publications, departmental memos and correspondence, loan agreements for exhibitions, and correspondence with fellow academics. Bowie's research in the arts of Thailand, China, Japan, and the Islamic World is represented in many of his publications, lecture notes, and photographs. Bowie's more personal files include an extensive series of correspondence with Charles and Piquette Cushing, select correspondence with his daughter Jocelyn, and Bowie's drafts of his memoirs. Also included are many of Bowie's colleagues' publications, and a number of photos and photo albums including portraits of Bowie, images of him working and traveling, and installation images from shows at the Indiana University Art Museum.
Separated Material
Photographs removed and stored with the Universty Archives Photograph Collection:
Series: Correspondence, folder "'Conversations with Adachi' general correspondence, circa 1983"
Series: Correspondence, folder "Japanese Drawing exhibition, general correspondence, 1975"
Series: Correspondence, folder "Loehr, Max, 1964-1977"
Series: Correspondence, folder "Warner Langdon, 1931-1952"
Series: Correspondence, folder "Warner, Langdon, memorial materials, 1995"
Series: Professional, subseries: Research, folder: "Various"
Related Material
Related photographs, including images of the "Arts of Thailand" Exhibition, are available in the University Archives Photographs Database.
Acquisition Information
Accession: 2018/060
Provenance
Collection was donated by the Bowie family, a donation facilitated by Fletcher Coleman, Adjunct Professor in Art History in May of 2018.
Transferred by Jocelyn Bowie, daughter of Theodore Bowie.
- Biographical, 1927–1974
  Scope and content note
  The biographical series includes a number of drafts and chapters from Bowie's memoirs, and histories on his work including the development of the Department of Fine Arts and the IU Art Museum, as well as his exhibitions. Small personal artifacts such as an address book and student artwork are included as well.
  - Addresses, undated (Box 1)
  - Archaeological Map of Thailand, undated (Box 1)
  - Bowie (Box 1)
    - Memoirs, miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
    - Memoirs My Early Life in Japan, 1905–1911, undated (Box 1)
    - Memoirs, semi-complete, undated (Box 1)
    - My career as an actor-producer-director, undated (Box 1)
    - Partial History of the IU Art Museum and Friends of Art, undated; (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - The Thai Show, undated (Box 1)
  - Exhibition Histories, undated (Box 1)
  - Drawings and Portraits, undated (Box 1)
  - IU Auditorium Blueprint, undated (Box 1)
  - IU Photographs and Image Copies, undated (Box 1)
  - The Maryland Bowies, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Renschler, William, student project, 1974; (Artist book featuring rubbings, watercolors and woodcuts) (Box 1)
  - University of California Senior Work, 1927 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1925–1995
  The Correspondence series contains lecture notes, personal correspondence including with Prince Diskul of Thailand, Herman B. Wells, and Erwin Panofksy, correspondence regarding exhibitions and catalogues, travel itineraries, film scripts, Bowie's own class notes, and scholarly articles. included as well.
  - Adachi Toyohisha, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Addresses and Itineraries, 1930 (Box 2)
  - Arkush, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Art of the Surimono general correspondence, 1966-1981 (Box 2)
  - Arts of Thailand (Box 2)
    - Catalogue materials, 1960-1975 (Box 2)
    - Contract copies, 1960 (Box 2)
    - General correspondence, 1962-1991 (Box 2)
  - Awards and Professional Societies, general correspondence, 1935-1976 (Box 2)
  - Bandy, W.T., 1975 (Box 2)
  - Bonwit, Stephen J., 1974 (Box 2)
  - Bowie, Jocelyn, 1975-1992 (Box 2)
  - Bowie, Marilyn, language and recipe notebook, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Bowie, Theodore (Box 2)
    - Apples and Persimmons, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Departmental Information, 1976-1989 (Box 2)
    - Phi Beta Kappa Initiation, undated (Box 2)
    - Memorials and remembrances, 1950-1995 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous from, 1963-1975 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous to, undated (Box 2)
    - Retirement and honors, 1976-1984 (Box 2)
  - Cahill, James, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Conversations with Adachi general correspondence, circa 1983 (Box 2)
    Separated Material
    Photographs removed and transferred to University Archives Photograph Collection.
  - Cranston, Fumiko, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Crawford, John, undated (Box 2)
  - Cushing, Charles and Piquette (Box 2)
    - 1936 (Box 2)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 2)
    - undated (Box 2)
  - Davezac, Bertrand, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Dupree, Louis and Nancy, 1973 (Box 2)
  - East – West in Art, general correspondence, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Edwards, Richard, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Eisenberg, Marvin, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Erotic Art correspondence, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Goodheart, John, 1981-1990 (Box 2)
  - Gottfried, Marion, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Gray, Basil, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Griswold, Alexander, 1968-1980 (Box 2)
  - Henderson, Mary and Harold, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Hillier, Jack, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Hope, Henry (Box 2)
    - 1981-1988 (Box 2)
    - Memorial tributes, 1989 (Box 2)
  - James, William, undated (Box 2)
  - Japanese Drawing Exhibition, general correspondence, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Katz, Hilda, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Keene, Donald, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Keyes, Roger, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Kleinbauer, Eugene, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Krieg, E. Michael, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Langdon Warner through his letters, general correspondence, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Loehr, Max, 1964-1977 (Box 2)
  - Matsubara Naoko, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Mayuyama Junkichi, 1968-1974 (Box 2)
  - Mitchell, Charles, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Morgan, Patricia, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Morley, Grace, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Nail Jr., Henry, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Nelson, Susan (to), 1980-1998 (Box 2)
  - Neperad, Ronald, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Panofsky, Erwin, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Peyre, Henri, 1948-1970 (Box 2)
  - Pozzatti, Rudy, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Raymond and Raymond, undated (Box 2)
  - Rickey, George, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Rosenfield, John, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Ryan, John, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Sachs, Paul, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Sansom, George, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Scott, Juliana, undated (Box 2)
  - Sickman, Lawrence, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Solley, Tom, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Studies in Erotic Art general correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Sullivan, Michael, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Togasaki, Fumiko, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Upton, Rick and Martha, undated; Includes small woodblock print sent to Bowie by the Uptons (Box 2)
  - The Vitality of the Classical Tradition general correspondence, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Waller, Bret, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Warner, Alice Sizer, 1967-1971 (Box 2)
  - Warner, Langdon (Box 2)
    - 1931-1953 (Box 2)
    - Memorial materials, 1955 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Dunhuang, 1925 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2)
  - Wells, Herman B., 1951-1975 (Box 2)
  - Wenley, Barclay, undated (Box 2)
  - Wildenstein, Georges, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Zervas, Walter, 1974 (Box 2)
- Professional, 1914-2008
  The Professional series includes research notes, lectures, exhibition catalogues, essays by Bowie, book reviews both by Bowie and of his publications, exhibition notices and reviews, newspaper clippings, student papers, publications and essays by Bowie's peers and colleagues.
  Arrangement note
  The Professional series is arranged into three sub-series: "Research," "Publications," and "Collected Materials". Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Research, 1954-1985 (Box 2)
    - Essays, 1966-1985, and undated (Box 2)
    - Lectures, 1971-1979 (Box 2)
    - Research Notes, 1937, and undated (Box 2)
    - Various, 1954-1962 (Box 2)
  - Publications, 1938-2004 (Box 3)
    - Ancient Indian Sculpture and Painting, 1964; (3 copies) (Box 3)
    - The Animal in Chinese and Japanese Art, 1952; (2 copies) (Box 3)
    - Apples and Persimmons, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Art from the Ends of the Earth, 1961 (Box 3)
    - The Art Museum as a Teaching Tool, 1969; (2 copies) (Box 3)
    - The Arts of Thailand, 1962; (2 copies) (Box 3)
    - The Arts of Thailand, 1962; Hardcover, fully illustrated (Box 3)
    - The Art of the Surinomo, 1979; (2 copies, one with decorative case) (Box 3)
    - Baudelaire and the Graphic Arts, 1957; (2 copies) (Box 3)
    - Book review album (to and from), circa 1960-1980 (Box 3)
    - Book Review Notes, circa 1986 (Box 3)
    - Conversations with Adachi, 1983 (Box 3)
    - The Drawings of Hokusai, 1964 (Box 3)
    - The Dream of the Rush Gatherer, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Exhibition Notices, 1952-1975 (Box 3)
    - Films on Art: A Critical Guide, 1957 (Box 3)
    - German Art in Our Time, 1958; 2 Copies (Box 3)
    - Islamic Art Across the World, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Reviews, 1953-1984 (Box 3)
    - Film sele'Arte, 1955; 2 Copies (Box 3)
    - The Many Faces of Japan, 1964; 2 Copies (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1980-2004 (Box 3)
    - One Thousand Years of Chinese Painting, 1968; 2 Copies (Box 3)
    - Oriental Art at Indiana University, 1953 (Box 3)
    - Painted Caves in the Gobi Desert, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Portrait of a Japanologist, 1982; 5 Copies (Box 3)
    - The Present Day Vitality of the Classical Tradition, 1958; 3 Copies (Box 3)
    - The Prevalence of Form, 1960; 4 Copies (Box 3)
    - The Radiant Buddhas, 1961 and undated (Box 3)
    - The Sculpture of Thailand, 1976 (Box 3)
    - The Sketchbook of Villard de Honnecourt, 1959; 2 copies, (Box 3)
    - The Third Art Film Festival, College Art Journal, 1957 (Box 3)
    - Unknown Sculpture of Thailand, 1972; 3 Copies (Box 3)
    - What to See in a Japanese Print, 1973; 3 Copies (Box 3)
    - "Word and Picture Relationships, 1938 (Box 3)
  - Collected Materials, 1914-2008 (Box 4)
    - Brown, Robert God on Earth, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Bulletin of the California Palace of the Legion of Honor, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Chevalier, Haakon Andrè Malraux and Man's Fate, 1933 (Box 4)
    - Conferences and Programs, 1953-1993 (Box 4)
    - De Gruyter, W. Jos.Drawings and Water-colors: Hokusai, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Elsen, Albert (Box 4)
      - Lively Art from a Dying Profession, 1960 (Box 4)
      - Rodin's Naked Balzac, undated (Box 4)
    - Exhibition Notices, circa 1935-2008 (Box 4)
    - Fogg Museum of Art Art: Genuine or Counterfeit?, 1940 (Box 4)
    - Frabetti, Giuliano (Box 4)
      - Hokusai E Hiroshige: Paesaggi, 1976 (Box 4)
      - Hiroshige: Imagini Della Natura, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Forrer, Matthi Essays on Japanese Art Presented to Jack Hillier, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Forrer, Matthi Hokusai: Prints and Drawings, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Gealt and Baden A Transforming Vision, 2006 (Box 4)
    - Government of Madras – Epigraphy, 1914 (Box 4)
    - Griswold, Alexander (Box 4)
      - Art from Siam, 1960-1961 (Box 4)
      - Siamese Inspiration and the Memory Picture, 1961 (Box 4)
    - Hammacher, A.M.Beeldendekunst, 1941 (Box 4)
    - Hashemeyan, Sayed K.M.Oriental Rugs, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Hillier, Jack Some ukiyo-e painters of the second half of the eighteenth century, 1977 (Box 4)
    - International House of Japan Bulletin, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Indiana University Art Museum 1941 – 1982, 2 Copies (Box 4)
    - Indiana University, Department of Fine Arts Bulletin, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Indiana University Fine Arts Department Twenty-Fifth Anniversary, 1966; 2 Copies (Box 4)
    - Indiana University Museum of Art Handbook, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Japan and Asia – Boston Book Company, undated (Box 4)
    - Janson, H.W.The Mirror of History, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Keyes and Morse Hokusai's Waterfalls and a Set of Copies, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Kobayashi Taichiro Hokusai and Degas, undated (Box 4)
    - Literary Review Quarterly, 1926 (Box 4)
    - The Medieval Craftsman and his Modern Counterpart, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin, 1987 (Box 4)
    - MFA Boston (Box 4)
      - Art and Artifice: Japanese Photographs of the Meiji Era, 2004 (Box 4)
      - Day and Night in the Four Seasons by Hokusai, 1957 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Signature of Artists, undated (Box 4)
    - Nelson, Susan Rocks Beside a River, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Nesbit, Joanne Bloomington Treasures: Alma Eikerman and Karl Martz, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Ogden, Annie The Hell Concept, 1974 (Box 4)
    - Ouwehand, C.An Annotated Description of Hokusai's Shūga Ichiran, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Rather, Clif and Lois Oh Yes, We Have Bananas!, 1974 (Box 4)
    - Rosenfield, John The Sedgwick Statue of the Infant Shōtoku Taishi, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - Rowshan-Araghi, Iradj Influences of Four Systems of Ideology on the Arts of Persia, undated (Box 4)
    - Shaw, Bernard Bernard Shaw's Rhyming Picture Guide, undated (Box 4)
    - Sickman, Luarence Some Chinese Brushes, circa 1939-1940 (Box 4)
    - Togasaki, Fumiko Hokusai's Surimono, 1980 (Box 4)
    - UCSB Constructivist Tendencies, 1970 (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan Museum of Art Bulletin, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - Whitefield, Sarah The Academic Tradition, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Whitlock, Jack The Jataka Tales, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Yoskiaki Shimizu Genji: The World of a Prince, 1982 (Box 4)
- Photographs, 1952–1984
  The Photographs series contains exhibition scrapbooks, photos of Bowie on his travels, as well as images of artworks featured in catalogs and exhibitions.
  - Album 7, Exhibition Scrapbook for The Arts of Thailand, Tokyo, 1962 (Box 5)
  - The Arts of Thailand IU Bloomington, Exhibition Scrapbook, 1960 (Box 5)
  - Exhibitions prepared at IU beginning March 1952, 1952-1965 (Box 5)
  - Islamic Art and Culture Exhibition Scrapbook, circa 1970 (Box 5)
  - One Thousand Years of Chinese Painting and What to See in a Japanese Print Exhibition Scrapbook, circa 1973 (Box 5)
  - Prints of Sharaku Exhibition Scrapbook, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Conversations with Adachi Scrapbook, 1982 (Box 6)
  - ACLS Exhibition, 1957-1958; Loose photographs (Box 7)
  - Ajanta, M.D., undated (Box 7)
  - Album 4, undated; Photo album with images of Bowie abroad, some in Dunhuang, China (Box 7)
  - Bowie Work Photographs, undated (Box 7)
  - Islamic Art Exhibition, circa 1970; Loose photographs (Box 7)
  - IU Art Museum, Statue of Acala, undated; Loose photographs (Box 7)
  - Japanese Drawings, undated; Loose photographs and negatives (Box 7)
  - Kurisada Images, undated; Negatives (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Negatives, undated (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Research Images, undated; Loose photos, contact sheet (Box 7)
  - Sharaku Exhibition, circa 1980; Loose photographs (Box 7)
  - Thai Art Exhibitions, circa 1952-1973; Loose photographs (Box 7)
  - Tun-Huang and Xian, May 1981, Scrapbook including photos and postcards (Box 7)
  - University of Michigan Gallery of Art, storage, 1954; Loose photographs (Box 7)
  - Washing the Elephant Research Images, undated; Loose photographs (Box 7)